恐龙曾统治地球
Dinosaurs ruled the planet
(大卫爱登堡主持)
超过一亿五千万年
for over 150 million years.
几乎在地球的每个角落都可以找到它们的踪迹
They occupied almost every cornerof the globe
而它们的体型和大小各异
and came in almostevery shape and size imaginable.
有些恐龙确实非常独特
Some were truly extraordinary.
如今 我们知道霸王龙是游泳健将
We now know that T. rex wasa powerful swimmer.
迅猛龙则是长着羽毛的狡猾猎手
Velociraptors were cunning,feathered hunters,
有些恐龙的行为相当怪异
and that some dinosaurs hadthe most bizarre behavior.
然而 几乎每天都有新的发现
But new discoveriesare being made almost every day
揭示更多关于六千六百万年前地球上生物的故事
that tell us more about lifeon this planet 66 million years ago.
本季的《史前星球》中
This time on Prehistoric Planet,
我们将展示全新的动物
we reveal new animals...
和关于它们寻找伴侣的新发现
and new insightinto their quest to find a partner,
抚养一个家庭所面临的挑战
the challenges faced by raising a family...
以及它们间重量级的战斗
and their titanic battles.
带领您穿越时光探访大自然最壮丽的那个时代
Journey to a timewhen nature put on its greatest show.
尽在《史前星球2》
This is Prehistoric Planet 2.
北美洲
广袤的内海
The coast of the vast inland sea
几乎将北美洲一分为二
that almost splits North America in half.
在南部 当潮水退去时
Here in the south, as the tide falls,
巨型生物被吸引至海岸线
giants are drawn to the shoreline.
这些阿拉摩龙身长超过30米
These Alamosaurs are a hundred feet long
重约80吨
and weigh some 80 tons.
它们是这片大陆上最大的恐龙
They are the largest dinosaurson the continent.
由于体型庞大没有掠食者能与它们一较高下
So huge that no predator can tackle them.
有些阿拉摩龙很长寿
Some live to a great age.
这只雄性已经70岁高龄
This male is around 70 years old.
这群恐龙中有很多可能都是它的后代
Many in the herdare likely to be his offspring.
然而 它漫长的生命即将走到尽头
But his long life is now coming to an end.
它庞大的身体开始衰弱
His immense body is beginning to fail him.
它可能活不过今晚了
He may not survive the night.
黎明时分
Dawn.
这些脚齿龙闻到了气味
And these troodontidshave picked up a scent.
它们会迅速调查任何新事物
They're quick to investigate anything new...
尤其是可口的食物
especially if it might be worth eating.
但要咬破约7.6厘米厚的兽皮它们却力有不逮
But biting through a three-inch-thick hideis beyond their power.
太郁闷了
Very frustrating.
霸王龙
Tyrannosaurus rex...
北美洲的顶级掠食者
North America's top predator.
它拥有长达15厘米的牙齿
With his six-inch-long teeth,
可以轻松撕开阿拉摩龙坚硬的皮肤
tearing through an Alamosaur'stough skin is not a problem.
霸王龙或许能欺负脚齿龙
T. Rex might be able to bully troodontids,
但这么大的一具尸体很快就吸引了更强大的竞争对手
but a carcass as big as thissoon attracts more formidable competition.
风神翼龙是一种巨型翼龙
Quetzalcoatlus, a giant pterosaur.
是为数不多能挑战成年霸王龙的生物之一
One of the few creaturesthat will challenge an adult tyrannosaur.
被它1.8米长的喙啄一下
One strike from its six-foot-long beak
很可能会让霸王龙失去一只眼睛
could easily cost T. rex an eye.
尽管如此 看来它并不打算让步
Even so,it seems that he's not going to back down.
但又来了一只风神翼龙
But the arrivalof a second Quetzalcoatlus...
这下局面就不一样了
changes the odds.
毕竟 两只喙比一只更致命
After all,two beaks are deadlier than one.
对霸王龙来说 现在的局面太危险了
For T. rex, this is now too dangerous.
有些战斗不值得冒险
Some fights just aren't worth the risk.
至少暂时 这些飞行巨兽赢得了胜利
For now, the flying giants have won.
它们很快就吃得饱饱的
They quickly eat all they can.
但霸王龙等它的飞行劲敌离开
But T. rex will almost certainly be backto claim his share
几乎一定会回来要自己那份
once his flying rivals leave.
环绕北美洲的海域中还有其他巨型掠食者
In the waters that surround North America,there are other giant predators.
但它们没有对手
But they have no rivals.
沧龙
Mosasaurs.
虽然外观酷似巨大的鲨鱼
They may look like huge sharks,
但它们实际上是一种水生蜥蜴
but they are in facta kind of aquatic lizard.
它们庞大的体型迅捷的速度和强大的下颚
Size, speed and powerful jaws mean
使得海洋中罕有生物能幸免于它们的捕食
that very few creaturesin the ocean are safe from these hunters.
在墨西哥湾 这只球齿沧龙正在寻找
In the Gulf of Mexico,this Globidens mosasaur is searching
一种特定的猎物
for one particular kind of prey.
楔碟菊石科的虎纹菊石
Tiger ammonites, Sphenodiscus.
每年 成群的雌性菊石从深海中游上来
Every year, huge shoals of females come up
向海岸迁徙
from deep waterand travel towards the coast.
它们最近都完成了交配每只都携带着成百上千个受精卵
They have all recently mated and each isnow carrying hundreds of fertilized eggs.
必须在浅水区产卵
The eggs must be laid in the shallows.
而沧龙正潜伏在那里 等待捕食
And that is where the mosasaur is waiting.
虎纹菊石本身就是猎手
Tiger ammonites are themselves hunters.
流线型的身形和强大的虹吸管
The combination of a streamlined profileand a powerful siphon enables them
使它们能够在水中飞速穿梭
to shoot through the water at great speed.
然而 沧龙同样具备极快的速度
But so can the mosasaur.
球齿沧龙的牙齿宽而圆能轻松咬碎菊石的外壳
Globidens has broad, rounded teeththat easily crack the ammonites' shell,
释放出使它们保持浮力的空气
releasing the air that keeps them buoyant.
失去空气的支持 菊石将无助地沉入海底
Without it,they sink helplessly to the seabed.
在菊石逃脱之前沧龙会咬坏尽可能多的猎物
Before the ammonites can escape,the mosasaur disables as many as it can.
终于可以大快朵颐了
Finally, time to tuck in.
尽管球齿沧龙已经捕杀了数十只菊石
Globidens may have killed dozens...
但这对整体菊石数量的影响微乎其微
but even this makes only a small impacton the overall numbers of ammonites.
绝大多数菊石幸存下来
Most of the shoal have survived
继续前往产卵地
and continue on their journeyto their spawning grounds.
这片岩石海床拥有众多缝隙和裂缝
The rocky seabed herehas many cracks and crevices,
成为菊石卵囊依附的理想场所
ideal places for attachingthe ammonites' precious egg sacs.
雌性菊石将卵投放其中
The females then abandon them.
而这个沿海的保育区将它们呵护得安然无恙
But safe in this coastal nursery,
在这里 这些卵会孵化成为下一代生命
these eggs will producethe next generation.
这些沿海水域充满着生机
These coastal seas are full of life.
然而在几百公里之外、不远的陆地上
Yet on land,and only a few hundred miles away,
却是一片荒芜
there is desolation.
在这里 地壳深处的强烈运动
Here, powerful movements deepin the earth's crust are beginning
开始抬升落基山脉
to raise the Rocky Mountains.
地貌发生巨大变化使这个湖与附近的河流相隔绝
The immense changes in the landscapehave cut off this lake from nearby rivers.
湖水在狂风和炎热夏日的阳光下蒸发
Its waters evaporate in the strong windsand intense summer sun.
其中溶解的矿物质开始达到有毒水平
And the minerals that are dissolved in itare beginning to reach toxic levels.
对大多数生物而言这种水毒性太大 无法饮用
For most, this water is simplytoo poisonous to drink.
尽管如此 这个地方每年都吸引了 各种各样的动物前来
Even so, every year this place is visitedby all kinds of animals.
地狱鸭成群结队
Flocks of Styginetta,
这种现代鸭子的原始亲戚于旅途中在此驻足
a primitive relative of ducks,stop here on their travels.
它们并不是这里的唯一访客
And they're not alone.
恐龙也来了
Dinosaurs are here too.
这是一个梳齿龙家庭它们有羽毛但不会飞
A family of Pectinodon.They're feathered but flightless.
这群小家伙由父亲带领着
And they're led by their father.
这些恐龙和地狱鸭被这里奇特的季节性财富
These dinosaursand the Styginetta are both drawn here
所吸引而来
by a strange seasonal bonanza.
就是苍蝇
Flies.
这些昆虫的幼虫能够过滤掉湖中的有毒盐分
The larvae of these insects are ableto filter out the lake's toxic salts,
因此 它们能大量繁殖
and, as a consequence,they thrive in immense numbers.
现在它们正在孵化成数以百万计的
Now they're hatching into adults...
成年苍蝇
in their millions.
是湖中所有访客们的丰富蛋白质来源
They are a rich and abundant sourceof protein for all the lake's visitors.
梳齿龙是相当聪明的恐龙
Pectinodon areparticularly intelligent dinosaurs.
它们很快就想出了捕捉苍蝇的巧妙方法
It doesn't take them long to work outthe best way to collect flies.
然而 它们的父亲盯上了更大的目标
But their father hashis eyes on a bigger prize.
梳齿龙不仅聪明
Pectinodon are not only intelligent,
还是非常高明的猎手
they're also very skillful hunters.
地狱鸭没有觉察到它正在靠近
The Styginetta areunaware of his approach.
得手了
Success.
这是一顿更丰盛的家庭大餐
A rather moresubstantial meal for the family,
倒也不错
and just as well.
然而 苍蝇在这里的停留时间有限
The flies will only be here for so long.
这个恐龙家庭将不得不到别处寻找食物
And the dinosaur familywill be forced to find food elsewhere.
在更远的北方
Further north,
落基山脉仍在缓慢上升
the Rocky Mountainsare still slowly rising.
同时创造出更高、更凉爽的景观
And as they do,they create higher, cooler landscapes
在这里 广阔的松树林繁茂生长
where vast pine forests flourish.
随着春天的脚步临近树林中回荡着奇怪的叫声
As spring arrives,strange calls echo through the trees.
这是北美最全副武装的
The mating season has arrived
一种恐龙的交配季节
for one of North America'smost heavily armed dinosaurs.
即三角龙
Triceratops.
每年 大量身型庞大的三角龙 会聚集在空地上
Every year, large numbersof these giants gather in clearings.
雌性们在此寻找理想的配偶
The females have come to choose a mate.
6吨重的雄性们通过激烈的争斗来展示自己的实力
The six-ton males fightand display their strength.
这只年轻的雄性看起来正值盛年
This young malelooks to be in prime condition.
它在炫耀着自己那壮观、长达1米的角
Showing offhis spectacular meter-long horns...
和鲜艳的头饰
and his colorful head-frill.
它的角看起来完美无暇
His horns appear perfect.
尚未在战斗中受损
Not yet damaged by battle.
然而 对于雌性来说
To a female, however,
没有任何磨损的角可能意味着潜在的致命弱点
the absence of any wear and tear mightsuggest a potentially critical weakness.
即缺乏战斗经验
A lack of experience.
这些聚会对三角龙来说至关重要
These gatherings are crucial eventsin the lives of Triceratops.
它们为成年三角龙提供了一年中最好的繁衍机会
They provide the best chance in the wholeyear for the adults to become parents.
来这里的并非只有怀揣梦想的年轻三角龙
And young hopefuls are notthe only ones here.
这只超过10吨、年龄达30岁的雄性三角龙
A 30-year-old maleweighing more than ten tons.
如果说有什么东西它拥有得多
If there's one thingthat he has in spades,
那就是几十年来经历的战斗磨砺
it's decades of wear and tear.
虽然年岁已高
He may be old,
但它依然强壮 足以挑战年轻的对手 无论这个对手看起来多么健康
but he's still strong enoughto challenge a young rival, however fit.
风险很高
The stakes are high,
可双方都不愿意让步
and neither is willing to back down.
经验丰富的老三角龙凭借4吨的体重优势
The veteranhas a four-ton weight advantage...
和丰富的战斗技巧 稳操胜券
and the skill to make it count.
年轻三角龙的角不再完美
The youngster's hornsare no longer perfect.
这头老三角龙的战斗力
The old bull's fighting prowess
显然给这头雌性三角龙留下了深刻的印象
certainly seems to have impressedthis female.
对于失败者来说 交配季节已经结束
For the loser, the mating season is over.
然而 它新赢得的战斗伤疤也许足以吸引
However, his newly won battle scarsmight be just enough to attract a female
下一次聚集到这里来交配的一个雌性
next time the herds gather here to mate.
像三角龙这样的植食恐龙
For plant-eating dinosaurslike Triceratops,
在遍布北美大部分地区的广袤森林中一年四季都能觅得
the vast forests that cover much ofNorth America offer plenty to eat
丰盛的食物
all year round.
然而 对于生活在寒冷的 美洲大陆极北地区的动物来说
But for those that live inthe cold far north of the Americas,
觅食就要困难得多
food is much harder to come by.
在北极圈内
Here within the Arctic Circle,
每年有三个月几乎看不见太阳
for three months of the year,the sun barely rises.
漫长的冬季过去 气温终于回暖
When its warmth finally returnsafter the long winter...
身披羽毛的似鸟龙迅速利用这一有利时机
feathered Ornithomimusare quick to take advantage.
这些敏捷的旅行者是所有恐龙中奔跑速度最快的
These fleet-footed travelers are amongthe fastest runners of all dinosaurs.
能够行进很远的距离寻找新鲜植被
Capable of covering vast distancesin search of fresh vegetation.
它们的速度如此之快掠食者很难捕捉到它们
They're so fast that they'revery difficult for predators to catch.
经过一个艰难的冬天
After a tough winter,
这头雌性白熊龙急需尽快捕获猎物
this female Nanuqsaurneeds to make a kill soon.
它是霸王龙的小亲戚 但更为敏捷 关键是速度更快
A smaller relative of T. rex,but more agile and, critically, faster.
由于无处藏身 所以偷袭猎物是不可能的
There is nowhere to hide,so a surprise attack is impossible.
相反 它依赖于制造恐慌
Instead, she resorts to creating panic.
它需要选定一个目标
She needs to pick out a single target...
并坚定地追击
and stick with it.
似鸟龙的爆发力使它们占据优势
The Ornithomimus' bursts of speedjust give them the edge.
每次失败的狩猎都会进一步消耗宝贵的能量
Each failed huntuses up more precious energy...
让这只雌性白熊龙更接近饿死的边缘
bringing her ever closer to starvation.
尽管春天已至
It may be spring,
但在如此靠北的地方凛冽的寒风会迅速导致气温下降
but this far north, freezing windscan quickly cause temperatures to fall.
零星的降雪和露出地面的岩石给了白熊龙第二次机会
Flurries of snow and a rocky outcropcould give the Nanuqsaur a second chance.
使其更难被发现
Now she's harder to spot.
每向前迈进一寸 它离成功就更近一步
Every inch forwardbrings her closer to success.
它锁定了目标
She selects her target.
它不能独享这份猎物
This prize is not only for her.
作为一个母亲
She is a mother.
这是它为孩子们准备的鲜肉大餐
Fresh meat for her youngsters.
也许这是几周以来的第一顿丰盛大餐
Perhaps the first for many weeks.
如果想让孩子们茁壮成长
If her babies are to thrive,
它将不得不一次又一次地复制今天的胜利
she will have to repeat today's successover and over again.
直至孩子们长大到能加入捕猎行列
Until her young are old enoughto join her in the hunt
并最终自力更生
and eventually fend for themselves.
在这片遥远、或许是最具挑战的
Here, in this remoteand perhaps most challenging frontier
北美大陆边疆
of the North American continent,
六千六百万年前
66 million years ago.
揭秘《史前星球》
为什么三角龙有扇状饰板?
这是史前地球上最令人瞩目的头骨之一
This is one of the most dramatic skullsfrom our prehistoric planet.
它属于一种叫做三角龙的植食恐龙
It belonged to a plant-eating dinosaurcalled Triceratops.
从其后脑巨大的扇状饰板
This dinosaur is instantly recognizable
便能一眼认出这种恐龙
from the massive frillat the back of its head.
然而 在发现第一块化石140年之后
But 140 years afterthe first fossil was found,
科学家们仍在探寻
scientists are still asking,
“这个扇状饰板是干什么用的?”
"What was the frill for?"
这些都是巨大的结构
These were enormous structures,
由大量骨骼和组织形成
so it's an enormous investmentin bone and in tissue
自然历史博物馆 保罗巴雷特教授
同时需要很多肌肉支撑这些结构
and also in the muscular effortto hold these structures up.
所有这些投入肯定意味着这些特征对动物的生活方式
All of this investment must meanthat these features are very important
非常重要
to the animal's way of life.
但如何重要呢?
But how?
三角龙化石上的受损证据显示
Evidence of injuryon Triceratops fossils suggests
扇状饰板在防御和战斗中很重要
that the frills were importantin defense and combat.
我们可以看到 头骨上的损伤
We can see lesions on the skull
自然历史博物馆
苏珊娜梅德门特博士
这些地方曾受到损害并已愈合
which are areas wherethe skull has been damaged and healed.
我们还能看到捕食者从这扇状饰板上咬下一大块的痕迹
We can also see where a predatorhas taken a chunk out of a frill.
这可能表明我们看到的是某种防御结构
That might indicate that we're lookingat some sort of defensive structure.
但故事并未就此结束
But the story doesn't end there.
另一种可能性是扇状饰板用于吸引潜在伴侣
Another possibility is that the frillwas used to attract prospective mates.
我们在现存的动物身上看到了类似现象
We see this in living animals
比如说 角这样的结构 显示出动物的健康状况
where structures like hornsshow off how healthy they are
以及谁更有可能繁衍出大量后代
and who's a good prospectfor producing lots of young.
就驼鹿而言
For a moose,
大鹿角使雄性更具吸引力
having large antlers makesthe male more attractive.
而这在性成熟时至关重要
Vital when it reaches sexual maturity.
那么 三角龙的扇状饰板是否也具有同样的作用呢?
Could the same apply tothe Triceratops' frill?
如果仅用于防御
If it was only for defense,
我们会期望它们
then we would expect to see them develop
在青少年时期和成年时期发展到相同的程度 但事实并非如此
to the same degreein juveniles as in adults, but we don't.
我们看到 它们在青少年时期要小得多
We see them being much smallerin the juveniles
直到很久以后 才真正发育成
and not really developinginto the very, very large structures
非常大的成年结构
of the adults until much later.
(三角龙头骨发育)
这并不是唯一证据
This isn't the only evidence
表明它们被用于性展示
that they were used in sexual display.
扇状饰板的表面有很多凹槽
The surfaces of the frillsare very heavily grooved.
这些凹槽可能携带着神经和血管
These grooves probably carried nervesand blood vessels
用于供应扇状饰板上皮肤的生长
that would have suppliedthe skin growing over those frills.
它的颜色可能非常鲜艳
This may have been very brightly colored,
这是一个很大的表面积可以让动物向潜在的伴侣炫耀
a big surface area for the animalto show off to potential mates.
科学家们如今认为
Scientists now believe that
三角龙最著名的特征确实具有多重功能
the Triceratops' best-known featurewas truly multipurpose.
既是有效的攻击和防御工具
Very useful for attack and defense...
同时也是吸引异性的理想选择
but also ideal for attracting a mate.
无论对敌对友 这都是令人敬畏的景象
It would have beenan awe-inspiring sight to friend or foe.